so we got a question on um
the two types of extreme mentioned in
the sutures so
[Music] to if
to if
the two types of extreme can be
clarified and what
and what
the middle way
is
it seems that the middle way cannot be
the way of moderation because moderation
still takes part in both extremes if one
is loving or hating the middleweight
cannot be a little bit of both
so
would it be correct to say that the
middle way
is the opposite way of whatever our
present craving is
for example when there is love one
should develop non-love and when there is hate
develop non-love and when there is hate
once you develop non-hate
so in dhammachaka sutta the buddha says
these two domains should not be visited
by one who has gone forth
the practice of central pleasure which
is inferior vulgar the way of ordinary
man ignoble
unbeneficial and the practice of self-modification
and the practice of self-modification
which is painful ignoble and
unbeneficial without going to either of these domains
without going to either of these domains
um extremes
the the target has awakened to the
middle way which is for developing
insight produces knowledge and leads to
calming full understanding to an ibana
the two extremes
the essential indulgence
and the um
self-modification usually
usually
commonly they're sort of um
watered down in the sense that
they're taken they're taken to mean like
this kind of
obvious um
overdoing of indulging of central
pleasures and like a obvious
self-evident like
self-torture or something like that but
it's it's um it's actually much more
subtle than that in a sense that uh
yes the extreme indulgence to attention
in sensuality
um but takes in the domain of central
pleasures but also that domain can be
very very subtle so even if you
engage in some subtle ways
um
with with centrality it's still within
the same domain of sensuality which
means middleweight does not apply to it
in the same sense
the self-modification the aesthetic
practice can be obviously
very coarse
very very like visibly ignoble
but that doesn't mean that it's it's it
um it's confined only to those extreme
examples there can be subtle ways of uh
engaging in the same type of behavior in
the in the same principle of
self-modification and then it still
partakes to that ins in that same domain
so it's equal ignoble
so in other words there is a spectrum of
of from subtle to cause and doesn't
matter what uh
uh and what place in that spectrum you
are if it's total sensuality it's still
the domain of central indulgence if that
spectrum is towards the
self-modification it's still within the
domain of self-modification so
middle way is neither so it doesn't
apply to any of those and the reason why
this needs clarifying is because
uh
in sort of in contemporary notions of
buddhism as i said things just naturally
are watered down so then people have
this view whereby as long as i don't
really overdo sensuality and is it long
if i don't overdo asceticism that's the
middle way
and that's exactly what this question
points out like
if it were only moderation means okay so
you could still have love towards
sensuality or hate towards pain and so
on uh and then you just need to sort of
be moderate in regard to two but
actually middleweight is the
the subtlest thing to see
it's not something you can arrive at
through mere
moderate practice
because if if they were possible we
wouldn't need the buddha um you know to
shape the universe when when he
discovers the middle way and so on it
would be something every other person
would sort of stumble upon
middleweight can only be discovered on
the level of uh
as it says here the uh
opposite way of wherever your present
craving is directing
so
if your present craving is towards
self-modification and denial
then the middle way is non-craving
towards modification and denial if your
present way is craving towards
sensuality and sense gratification the
middle way is
uh non-desire towards sensuality so
that's why it's not
it cannot be adhered to as a set of
behavior or method or do this and you
follow the middle way
because as we often say
where the middle way will be found
depends on where your attention is
currently aiming at your intention sorry
so that's why knowing your intentions
means knowing where things are rooted in
in your mind is this rooted in desire or
real will or denial or any of the
hindrance well the middle way would be
the absence of those unbeneficial states
first you need to be sense restrained
sure don't be spilling out
then you need to know the intentions
behind your actions so if you are
aiming at um
i don't know some some some
some practice aesthetic practice say you
got inspired and you want to be
staying awake all night and meditating
every day
that in itself it's it's neither good
nor bad
it's your motivation behind wanting to
do that
so the reasons for you wanting to do
such practice that's what you would see
if this is wholesome ron wholesome
and that needs to be seen because
otherwise you just um
you just um
the entire the entire project the entire
um inspiring project is rooted in an
unwholesome intention so the roots are
not wholesome they're rooted in
probably a degree of ill will denial
aversion and that's why it's taking you in that
and that's why it's taking you in that
direction that's why the buddha would
never didn't want to prescribe
the ascetic practices as mandatory
practices because
because
they don't always result in uprooting of
passion in themselves by themselves they do not
in themselves by themselves they do not
guarantee uprooting of passion and ill
will on the contrary if they were rooted
in in wrong intentions in intentions of
conceit intentions of aversion
intentions of restlessness and
impatience then they will increase your passion and
then they will increase your passion and
your aversion and your conceit and your
impatience the mind will grow if
the mind will grow if
things rooted in on wholesome intentions
when they're rooted in unwholesome
intentions are not pursued not welcomed
which means
certain things that are kind of neutral
in themselves
can sometimes be rooted in unwholesome
intentions sometimes in wholesome
intentions so it's not that you must
never do them or that you can always do
them so things you should never do are things
so things you should never do are things
that are against the precepts that's
very clear it doesn't require any
great philosophical pondering and wisdom
just requires a bit of faith and taking
on those behaviors
as a as a mode of being that you train
within now within the precepts
now within the precepts
there will be things that are as i said
sometimes you know beneficial sometimes
not externally they look the same those
things but uh internally they are completely
but uh internally they are completely
different things because they're rooted
in different type of intentions that's
why it's it's um
it's it's um
it's paramount really to recognize that
okay so within the precepts
i need to um
pretty much refrain an impulse that you
know most people have
to kind of overly
overly
clarify the set of behavior and methods
and meditations or set of determinations
in ascetic practices and instead
within the precepts
stay on the level of that kind of
ambiguity of my own intention and
sometimes that day sometimes like that
because that's where the practice is and
you can ask yourself which is harder
to
go along with centrality
or to
build up a determination and just say no
to everything or is it harder to stay
on the level of doubting mind
that that tries to pressure you to act
that tries to pressure you to act
constantly
that refuses to listen to the reason so is it
refuses to listen to the reason so is it
harder to stay on that level and endure
the mind pressuring you
then to just overly determine and
dismiss that whole domain and just
commit to a blind practice of i'll never
sleep at night or i will walk six hours
a day doing work meditation or i will
never speak or i will never do this or
then go the other extreme and just do
you know everything completely
unrestrained so it's always that similar of the deer
so it's always that similar of the deer
herd and debate
like um you can eat the bait carelessly
or you can completely
say no to all types of food because it
might contain the bait but then you'll
starve or you will learn how to discern where
or you will learn how to discern where
the bait is and then just don't eat that
so that's why that's where the middle
way is the hardest way
and that's why the other way is the
ignoble way because it will not bring
understanding although externally you
know some severe practices of
some severe practices of
self-modification
are far more like
inspiring to the eye like the commitment
determination the persistence and so on
the endurance but internally if they're
completely rooted in in your desire
conceit and power of will that refuses
to basically endure things on the level
of
mind want like mind intending to do
things out of desire and you're not
giving into that it's easier to just
cover up the desire and commit to a set
of blind practice that won't make you
think about it but that that's the point
it will have to run out
sooner or later that will have to run
out as the simile of the data says and
then you go back eating all the food
carelessly because you don't you haven't
learned where the bait is
so knowing the intentions behind your
actions behind the actions of the body
the speech the mind throughout the day
on the basis of impeccable precepts
that will result in
like sustained recollectedness mindfulness
sustained recollectedness mindfulness
it will result in composure and it will
result in as i often say enduring things
on the right level
and then
if through that framework
you see that increasing the certain
aesthetic aspects of your life
introducing some asceticism into your
life will actually bring this further to
will actually bring this further to
fulfillment this context this
understanding this clarity but then it
will be again it will be guided by the
right perspective
but if you're just doing it because it
kind of makes you feel good makes you
feel righteous makes you feel inspired
then it's equally equally ignorant as it
is to engage in sensuality if your
domain of sensuality and domain of
self-modification and denial well the
domain of enduring your intentions
without acting out of them is the domain
of the middle way and that's the domain
where the hindrances are where the
pressure and pains of desire
of ill will of sloth and laziness of
restlessness of worry of doubt
and that's why that's what the practice is
that's why that's what the practice is
if you were to endure things on that
level then your mind will have to grow
then your mind will have to grow
even if you never engage in you know
some extreme aesthetic practices
but if you never lose the sight of the
domain of your own intention like of of
your own
uh choices you're making and that's why
you know i i i keep saying that
you know
people's minds generally and stress that
enter your mind and your life and it
burdens you and overwhelms you
is not the result of some metaphysical
ignorance nor is the result of you not having
nor is the result of you not having
practiced focusing um or noting
meditation um or watching your cessation
long enough no
unwholesome states
always there's only one way that those
unwholesome states can enter your mind
and and burden your life
and that is intentional choice
towards greed or lust
towards ill will aversion and towards
distraction and indolence that's it
so it's not because you slipped the
moment you didn't watch your mind close
enough you wouldn't concentrate it
enough no it's because you still keep
choosing consciously
like um
in in full awareness or although you
might you know ignore that but every
choice is something you're conscious of
and the disturbances and unwholesome states
the disturbances and unwholesome states
can only enter through such choices and
persist then you need to stop making such
then you need to stop making such
choices
sustain that state of not
making choices rooted in great diversion
delusion and then they will cease to
persist those unwholesome states will
fade away because you're not adding more
fuel to their fire and yeah so so and
then if sometimes you're not a person i
think oh but no i still need to
concentrate in order to be able to catch those
in order to be able to catch those
choices again choices are not on the
level of like a momentary flow of your
consciousness and so on that you must
kind of mustn't blink because you miss
your choice no it's a it's quite evident
choice is something you intentionally
intend something you choose to make
something you choose to act out of
something you choose to welcome
accept delight in
and so on
so it's
it's not something you can be unaware of
or it's uh or something that can
accidentally slip you
and that's exactly why
fundamentally a path to nibana and
enlightenment is always within
your reach and within your own control
in that sense
not that you can choose nibana directly
but you can abstain from choices that
have taken you away from that which
nibbana is that is keeping you away from
that which nibana is
so if those choices are abandoned
and then purified
whether you want it or not
your mind is heading towards nirvana
in terms of blanket rules and behaviors
that's the precepts that's it
but then if that's just to contain you
so that you can start seeing your
intention intentions towards same things
intentions towards same things
rooting in different intentions
different things rooted in the same
intention and so on
so once you're contained within the
precepts your intentions have potential basically
your intentions have potential basically
to become uh to be understood to be seen
even more clearly your choices
responsibility for those and so on so
then then the question is just um
of not falling into the trap of
or giving in to that kind of
path of less resistance which is the
path of further than adopting sets of
behaviors techniques
and methods
so that you don't have to think about or
endure the states of doubt of in your
mind the states of uncertainty was it
rooted here was it rooted there but it
was the same thing here but it was
different attention well it was the same
intention but it was different thing all
that needs to be endured until the
clarity is developed and you endure that
on the basis of not breaking the
precepts but that's unpleasant that can
be a pleasant and as the buddha said in
the studies how unpleasant that will be
well depends on how much
your mind was dependent on sensuality
beforehand so how much
like how many how often the hindrances
would be would be pressuring you and
pulling you depends on basically how
often you were giving in to them in the
past and uh you you can't really know
that up until you're free from them and
then it doesn't really matter so the
point is to endure things on that
unpleasant level when it's unpleasant
it's not always going to be unpleasant
and not not not give in to that
like overly defined now sets of practices and
overly defined now sets of practices and
methods and sensation watching and
noting or whatever else techniques they
will then sort of
make it more mechanical step-by-step
practice so that you don't have to
endure the unpleasant state while at the
same time that entire commitment to that
step-by-step mechanical practice as i
call it is rooted in the intentions that
you're ignoring
and so at any given time you can pick up
your practice doesn't matter how much
you straight so to speak
if you
uncover the the intentions that you are
already aware of that you already know
so and that would be the practice of the
middleweight so see you're not giving
into centrality but you're not overly
denying now either you're enduring
things so in the symbol of the deer the
smart the wisest dear heard
learned that they can't say no to all
the food because they'll starve
so they learn how to endure the pressure
the pull
the the the enchantment of the bait
and not act towards the bait so that
then they can eat other food that's not
the bait but until you have endured a
bait long enough you won't see what
what's paid what it isn't uh and that's
that's the whole practice so not giving
in but not running away from it either
not welcoming it but not denying it
allowing it to rise persist and endure
it